[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right welcome to the stoa i am peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
and for those of you don't know the
store is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of this
very moment and today we have a special
sunday event the title dying
east and west with daniel p brown
so this is a 90-minute session uh it's
recorded and it will go on youtube
uh and the mc for the day is
a humble human being because that's how
he wanted to be known by uh
cody taff uh i'll hand it to cody in a
moment he'll introduce daniel introduce
how the session's gonna run today
and uh and we'll go from there so that
being said
i will take daniel in
you can unmute yourself now
hey daniel uh
okay so uh daniel if you don't mind i'm
gonna um i'm gonna dote on you for a
second
um since i don't think um i don't think
everyone knows who you are so
daniel's um dr daniel p brown
um is the director uh center of
integrity of
psychotherapy in newton massachusetts
associate clinical professor of
psychology at harvard medical school's
medical school
it's the author of 15 books including
transformations of consciousness with
ken wilbur and jack engler
he studied meditation practice for 45
years beginning with reading patanjali's
yoga sutras and its commentaries in
their original sanskrit
studied tibetan for um
for many years uh translated uh texts
for 10 years he can speak to this and
the task that he was given to translate
11 different texts and i think he just
finished up on that
as a western psychologist he spent 10
years conducting outcomes research on
beginning
advanced meditators top meditation
retreats for 20 years
and the list goes on and on
um so welcome daniel hi everybody nice
to see you
um and i want to just uh set the setting
of how this
um how this event came to be
um a few uh stowites
and i threw a little private session to
kind of get a vibe of what was going on
in the stowawa and maybe
get a sense of what the stoa wanted as
an essence
um and it was a fun little event and
what showed up was something around
dying and and mortality and existence in
general and it was really beautiful
and one thing that came up was the idea
that we're in the middle of this
pandemic and hundreds of thousand people
have died
many of them have died alone um this
uh you know hearing that i was reminded
of actually daniel speaking to this very
thing
um and i was reminded of a grieving
practice that um that he knows
at the same time and why this is so
important is because we haven't dealt
with this in any way new york times put
out a list of
you know people that died in the middle
of this and i think that's about
all that the media or leadership is
actually done in a form of
of grieving a time like this with such
loss and
loneliness and at the same time that
speaks a little bit to leadership
um it speaks to a little bit of lack a
lot a bit of lack of leadership
and i think the stoa actually really
attracts a lot of
a lot of individuals that that may have
that in them you know they're having
these conversations that are actually
very hard and that
that these conversations are what uh
what makes leaders
and in that i'm reminded of daniel
schmokenberger saying you know we have
the power of gods right now as humanity
but
we don't have the wisdom to wield that
and
in that i'm i'm i'm reminded and and
question what are the what are the paths
and the tools that we can actually gain
that wisdom
and we have mindfulness uh you know
running rampant
and meditation techniques running
rampant in the west
but daniel's a part of a lineage that's
something very special in it and it uh
and he's gonna speak to this
um that has a goal of awakening and and
perhaps that goal can
and these practices can lead us to uh
awakened leaders and uh
buddhas in the west so uh daniel i'm
gonna let you take this and um
we'll go from there thank you so i'm
gonna talk about
western approaches to dying and grieving
process
first and i want to talk about the
approaches in tibetan buddhism
so from a western perspective
grieving is a natural process to the
loss of someone
so when someone dies we we first go
through a stage of disbelief we don't
really
get it that the person has died we don't
know we don't accept it we want to deny
it
so we push out the memories and the
feelings of the person
and then they alternate between coming
back to us and then we
work back and forth between denying the
feelings and memories and
having the experience of them and over
time we eventually work it out and this
when the
grieving process comes to a close that's
the normal grieving process
but for the last
100 years we've through remaining
there's a psychoanalytic tradition
we've just looked at the grieving
process in great detail
and what we know is that some people
don't go through the normal grieving
process it doesn't end
we call that complicated morning and
what complicates the grieving process is
usually conflict
so the relationships that we're closest
to and with the least conflictual are
the ones that are easiest to mourn
but the ones that we're more conflicted
about are the ones the hardest to mourn
and
i been interested particularly in
grieving
and some 20 years ago i found a grieving
protocol that was developed in australia
in the 1980s
it was an obscure journal of hypnosis in
australia
and what it described was 63 cases of
complicated bereavement
that were resolved completely in less
than three sessions
the average time was one or two sessions
and the maximum was three sessions that
raised my eyebrows
so we looked at the protocol and as was
often
in in that generation people described
in general what they did but they
described in great detail
what they did so we didn't we couldn't
extract
the method easily from the text that was
written about it
so we put it in the process as well as
we could we used it for over 200 people
and i found the same results
that we had a complete resolution of
complicated morning in
less than three sessions each time
over 200 sessions so that amazed me
so this became very popular over time
and we sort of filled it out to the
mainstream i started teaching grief
workshops around the country
and then internationally and uh
it became a very popular way of doing
the grieving process i will do that
method with you
at the end of this talk before we get to
the question and answer we'll actually
go through it
so your task is to think about some loss
that you never really fight
got over and we'll we'll go through it
as a process
is you can do it on somebody
individually that you it doesn't have to
be
lost through dying it can be also a
relationship you never quite over the
person still
they're still alive but they still lost
so you can use it either way
let me turn now to we'll come back to
this exercise i'll do it for you the
best way of doing it is just do it it's
very powerful
but when i come back to the western
eastern approach to dying
and in indo-tibetan buddhism
there's a series of methods called
consciousness transfers
power the word literally means to shift
location
and that's the method i'm going to talk
about now
these represent lineage traditions and a
lineage means that there are special
instructions and the emphasis on linear
traditions is to focus on the actual
experience of an awakened mind
shifting from an ordinary mind to awaken
mind
and you're given detailed instructions
which are usually kept secret
so you don't intellectualize about them
they're given from master to student
from heart to heart
they'll call them special pith
instructions they're given from master
to student from heart heart from
generation to generation
and they describe exactly how to look at
the take a certain perspective of you
sets up your meditation experience so
you can actually have the experience of
awakening
and there are fifth instructions for
every level of practice from the
beginning of practice
to dismantling the structures of the
mind to
having the taste of awakening to working
through all negative states and
developing the flourishing positive
states and then these are special
centerpiece instructions for
full enlightenment so each set of piston
structure is like a key that opens up a
gateway to a whole
level of practice in lineage traditions
and the the mindfulness is very popular
in the west
and i did outcome studies as a western
psychologist on mindfulness for 10 years
but i think what's happened is it's
become commercialized is that it's
forgotten its roots
i say that as someone who knows this
tradition well i in the 1970s i went to
burma
i had a special visa as western as we
only had a week's long visa but
mahasi said i was a great teacher in
burma came to the u.s and i did a course
with him
and i invited him to harvard to give a
talk on mindfulness meditation and while
he was at the after he finished the talk
he was
having lunch with him and he said come
to burma i said well that's all good and
well but i can't come to permanent
because they're going to get a week's
visa he said no i get a special visa
view so my visa was
as long as i meant it i could stay in
the country as soon as i stopped
meditating i had to leave
so i stayed for about four months and
went through all the stages of the
practice with him
and including a taste of awakening in
that tradition
but as it's got more popular mindfulness
is becoming just a way of becoming aware
it's ordinary awareness so the true
people are training the continuity of
ordinary awareness and that's different
from awakened awareness
and so in lineage traditions the whole
emphasis on
awakening we say that awakening is the
confluence of all the teachings
if it doesn't lead to that then you're
not doing it right
and then you refine the awakening so you
have it all the time in all situations
we have the only western neuro circuitry
study on awakened mind
we did a study last year with judd
brewer when he was at umass medical
school he's now at brown
and the sponsored by the fetzer
foundation and i gave them
30 subjects who had a taste of awakening
and we scanned them
and and looked at what the brain was
doing when they shifted from ordinary
mind to awaken mind
and what we found is very unusual
there's an area of the parietal system
that shifts from ordinary awareness to a
more global
huge awareness this is like big
perspective taking
and that area of the brain got activated
but what we saw
in all 29 subjects was gamma activity
that is
maximum output that means all the cells
in that region of interest are all
firing simultaneously
at once so wake means awake it's a very
specific finding
[Music]
if you stabilize awakening then you have
it all the time you live in that state
all the time
and then you can set up a point of view
that you can
uh start eradicating all
karmic memory traces by holding a
certain
meditation practice it takes about eight
years to do that and what happens is you
exhaust
all negative negative states and you
negative states mass the positive state
so there's a flourishing of 80 positive
states of mind that come out
all at once just like that imagine
living in a state of mind where there
are no negative states in your
experience
left in only positive states i happen to
think that state of what's called sange
and tibetan
has profound implications for mental
health and
we now have enough subjects we can do
that so we're starting to look at the
sooner circuitry of that
and i think what we're going to find is
a dmr activity in the media orbital
frontal cortex which is the
positivity center of the brain and the
social connection center of the brain
and compassion center of the brain
that's our working hypothesis gamer
activity in that area of the brain
so that's the unique contribution of
lineage traditions they focus on the
actual experience of awakening and
refining of that to full enlightenment
and they give you special detailed pith
instructions to help open that up
i'm going to talk about the lineage
tradition more specifically about the
dying process
and it's the the set of exercises are
called consciousness transference
and there are four perspectives on that
that i'm going to go through just
briefly
the first is what's called external
consciousness transitions
second is internal consciousness
transference the third is secret and the
fourth is very secret
i want to give you an overview of each
of those practices
external consciousness transfer and
support you do while you
after you finish 100 000 preliminaries
in tibetan buddhism
it takes about two to two weeks to four
weeks to do it
and what you do is you imagine a a seed
energy drop about the size of a quarter
about this big
you place it in the central channel
central channel goes from the
we call the juncture which is four
fingers below the navel
it runs along the front of the spine and
goes straight up to the crown
so what you do is you place the the the
energy drop in the upper part of the
central channel just above the heart
and what you do is you you you imagine
pushing it up the central channel to
widen the central channel the upper part
of the central channel
and you make a sound
and eventually the you open up that
central channel the upper central
channel
in such a way that it hits the crown of
your head and you
keep forcing that energy drop up and
after about two weeks what happens is
that
you you move the crown plates and it
makes a hole
[Music]
and that will be accompanied usually by
the leaking of fluid
and a swelling of this little swelling
that happens in here
and at that point you go to the teacher
those are called signs of progress
talk signs of progress and then you'll
take a straw from a broom
you know put it right into the skin and
it goes right into this
it goes right because you move the
plates out of the way
so you've opened up the upper part of
the central channel
and what you do is you plug it with a
seed syllable you you plug the hole
you go out and you live the rest of your
life at some point
when the process of dying what you do is
you it's like an ejection seat in the
jet fired fighter
what you do is you you you blow the
the indestructible essence in
it at the point of conception there's an
introductory lesson it's like a computer
chip that has all the memories of your
practice lives and
[Music]
it's lodged in your heart at conception
and
when you die the chakra knots loosen and
that that infrastructure lessons is
freed up and floats in the central
channel and what you do is you you
when you when you see the signs of dying
you you
you enter into meditation and you you
blow it out the top of your head
and if you blow it out there you you
come you come out any different orifice
you come out your ears you can come out
your mouth it can come out
your ass you can come out anywhere but
none of those will lead to a good birth
lets you blow out the crown
and if you have voluntary control over
the process of transition of that
indestructible essence
it goes directly to what we call the
awaken dharmakaya space
and you you you you become a full buddha
then you can intentionally manifest any
form you want
in any multiple forms even so that's
what
power is used as a backup so if you
don't become buddha during a lifetime
and you fail at the practices of
meditation you're doing during the
lifetime
the backup plan is that when you have
external power
you can leave your consciousness when
you
leave the body and force it out the body
through the crown
and it immediately it becomes awake in
dharmakaya space
that's external power now
there's a controversy and a tradition
about external power
and that is that in the one of the books
i translated in the bond tradition
called the final stages the practical
guide to the stage of ah
which is 14 stages from beginning of
practice all the way through full
enlightenment in 14 lessons and sort of
like the
quick managed care version of
enlightenment
we translated that but there's 14
sessions in some and there's 15 sessions
another and there's a debate about
whether they should include the poor
practice in it
and the dominant consensus was that not
to include it because you
undermine people's confidence by giving
them poor practice as a backup plan
put the emphasis on having them become
fully booted during lifetime
and then if they don't do it then you
give the back a plane later in life it's
the external power
and that's the way that the tradition
usually does it
internal power is how you use the dying
process
itself during the actual dying
process to become a buddha and there are
three stages of dying process what first
is called the chikibardo
which is literally means the the time
the
the dying process itself it literally
means the
in the jaws of death while you're in the
early stages of dying
that's the best opportunity to become a
full buddha
if not during your lifetime and that's
called internal power
and if you don't miss it then the second
bartow is called the bottom of
of dhammadatu chernibado
and the third is the bottom of rebirth
and
the first is that when an internal power
the first opportunity or three
opportunities you get
first opportunity is during the jaws of
dying
so what will happen is that the elements
of the body dissolve and
the elements that bother to support the
mind so all conceptual thought stops
all perception stops so if you open your
eyes you don't see anything anymore
you don't hear anything anymore and
what's left is an
infinite field of lucid awakened
awareness
if you recognize that for what it is we
call that the clear light of the dying
process
during that time when all thoughts and
percept ordinary perception stops
which would ordinarily serve as
distraction to you if you recognize that
clear lucid
bright awakened awareness as as awakened
awareness
then you become a buddha on the spot so
the best preparation for dying is
awakening during the lifetime
so you can use what's called the clear
light of dying to recognize and say this
is familiar
i know this that's called that's the
first chance you get if you miss that
chance
then there's a second after death state
called the border of dhammadatu
and i like to call it the sound and
light show you get
pairs of lights one's bright and one's
very bright and the other one's faint
and light
and in the background there are sounds
like the continuous sound of thunderclap
it's very loud sounds and you can use
the sounds and lights
to see through them as insubstantial not
not as
is real real substantial not like a
reality out there
you have to see it as is just mental
constructions the mind is throwing up
these metal constructions and if you see
them properly as mental constructions
and don't get caught up in them or react
to them then you can use that as a
platform to
see beyond those constructions to the
clear light of awaken mind again so
that's the second
you can use the sound and light show if
you miss that then
what happens is content starts to come
back and depending on
the comic influences of your lifetime
it's going to determine which
which form of the six realms of
existence whether you're going to come
back as a human
whether you're going to come back as a
god as a demigod as a animal as a
hungry ghost or as a hellbear being
depending on how you lived your life
you know what the comic influences are
and what happens is that the early in
that what's called the
trinidad or the bottom of of
possibility of rebirth
what happens in that bardo is that you
you you have a mental body
and your senses are back you can hear
people
in who after you've died in that third
bottle or third after death state
you can see people who are survived your
death
but they don't they don't respond to you
if you talk to them they don't respond
to you
so at some point you figure out that
you're dead
you don't know that right away but
anything the mind focuses on
if you thought about going to some place
just like that you you're immediately
there
you say whoa that's amazing so you infer
from all those
things magical abilities that you
probably are dead at now
and that people can't respond to you
anymore
they still have an influence on you for
example if relatives pray for you
they can have a positive influence they
can calm your mind state if your master
prays for you they can have an influence
so the idea is you have three chances in
that
process of what's called internal
consciousness transference
to become a buddha first is during the
process of dying when
all the content of the mind stops and
you can recognize that
infinite vast lucid
field of awareness as awakened awareness
or you can recognize the
sound and light show as
just empty visions like rainbow light in
the sky
insubstantial yet occurring vividly or
you can recognize the content that comes
up and
and it's harder to recognize the content
because it's like this lifetime
you have three chances each one with
progressively different
slightly different odds less odds to
become fully
enlightened again if you miss those
opportunities you get reborn again and
you have to start over again
now there's a third one called secret
power and that's very rare
and let's suppose somebody dies of
suicide or they die suddenly and they
didn't have a chance they died
tragically of sudden
accident there are certain
llamas who know something about adorable
what they'll do is they'll they'll grab
that indestructible essence out of the
air like a cell phone number
they know how to grab it with sound and
then they'll
shoo they'll soothe it and comfort it
and then you know to do
to compel it into dhammakaya space
so a great llama who knows this secret
poor practice can actually take somebody
who's died
and who would probably have a bad
rebirth because because they they
suicided or something like that or
somebody would get a tragic accident and
bad circumstances of their death who
would obviously be covered by
enormous amount of fear when they're
dying out of compassion they can take
this
indestructible essence clean it off and
populate in a waking down mackay space
it's a great
gift to give that to somebody and
there's
very few llamas who know that and one of
the llamas who i talked with rahab tuku
who was actually my roommate in the
1980s
and he's the ammunition of promise
ambava i didn't know that at the time
when he was with my roommate but
he was a great master in buddhism he
just died this last year
but he's his monastery in sichuan china
does this special secret power so we've
sent him a number of people who
we over the years who he did that with
and the fourth is called very secret
poem and this is
what's known as rainbow body so great
masters
can when they die they can actually use
the dying process
to dissolve the physical body and there
are four practices that are done
to develop what's called grade
consciousness transference a rainbow
body
the first one is
the first two are what are called
treacher or thoroughly cutting through
practices in zochin and the second ones
are
what are called bypassing
we work with four levels of visions
those are the more advanced practices
what you do in the first practice is
that you
once you have a taste of awakening which
is an infinitely vast
field of limitless timeless
boundless brilliantly lucid awakened
awareness love
and you operate out of being that
that's your basis it's it's not
localized
it's stunningly bright and lucid and
clear
awake sacred
and loving that's the awakened mind
and
in this practice
what you learn to do is
when you first have that experience it
changes everything it moves your heart
you you feel like it's familiar to you
you recognize that you're coming home
and it changes everything in your life
but you'll probably fall out of that
view
the ordinary habits of the mind come
back so you have to then set up that
view to stabilize awakening
on the pillow first so what you do on
the pillow is you
set up the view that opens up this shift
to ordinary mind to awaken mind
you set it up so you experience it
frequently
for longer duration and more and more
immediately
and the sign of progress you're looking
for is that on the pillow
whenever you set up the view you don't
have to go through all the steps it was
ordinary shift from ordinary mind to
awaken mind
it will happen quickly and immediately
once that happens and you on the pillow
you shift to awakening
you get off the pillow and you start
engaging in activities
it's easy to maintain awakening when
you're out in nature by yourself
but it's much harder to you stay in a
stabilized awakening when you're talking
and conversing with somebody
or when you are working on your computer
when i worked with my my my the best
teacher i had was
his holiness men retrieving the
indigenous lineage holder for the bond
for the last
10 years he died a year ago but he was
the best teacher i've ever had i've
worked with tibetan vision for 50 years
now
but um
[Music]
when i first went to him i could get a
taste of awakening at the end of a
10-day retreat pretty regularly after 40
years of
practice he said come to me i can help
you with this
so i spent a month with him and all he
had to do was
sit outside in his office and he had a
steady stream of people and i'd have to
converse with him and maintain awakening
while i was conversing with them and i
have to work on my computer and
translate while i was thinking i had to
maintain awakening
and after about a month i could pretty
much hold the awakening all the time
including in deep sleep and dreams
so that's the after if you hold
awakening all the time then you
you hold that vast expanse as your view
in its limitless expanse of timeless
awareness
and you let everything arise within it
and whatever arises within that
you see as the lively expression of
awakened awareness
so all thoughts become lively awakened
awareness all pers
all emotions become lively awakened
awareness all sights all
sounds the body the body sensations
become lively awakened awareness it's an
uninterrupted dance of life and awakened
awareness
and then you hold both views
simultaneously the infinite vast expanse
and the uninterrupted liveliness of what
arises within that experience
and you hold it in such a way that you
don't engage anything that comes up
mental engagement in zochin or
completion meditations
is what causes what causes karmic memory
traces to form
so if you hold this view and you let
everything arise and you don't engage
anything
moment by moment by moment by moment it
forces the mind to release calming
memory traces
if you do that after it becomes an
automatic process you do it 24 7
and and after a while after about seven
or eight years there's no
negative states left it's called
dominator exhaustion you exhaust all the
negative states that would otherwise
comically ripen and since the negative
states mass
positive states you get a flourishing of
80 to 85 positive qualities at once
and that's the state of mind that you
live in from there
so that process
is what you start with in
in when you do great consciousness
transference very secret power
during that if you do that process in in
in meditation is during your lifetime
and you have some the experience of
what's called
complete purification in the flourishing
of positive states what's called sange
in tibetan
then while you're dying and you read the
signs of dying and you know you're ready
to die
you enter that same experience of
meditation
and you intentionally dissolve what's
residual of the physical body
and after three days into the dying
process the body will disappear
now it's said that there's a subtle
particulate matter of the body that
doesn't disappear but as
seen by others it will seem like the
body disappears all that's left is
the hair and nails the inanimate
substance of the body but the bones of
the
body is completely gone it's all changed
into light and what will float into
space after three days is
a spectacular display of rainbow lights
circling in in in the air and that will
last for
several days or something several weeks
that's called rainbow body
there's no physical body left the second
way of doing that
what's called authority cutting through
practice way of doing a rainbow body is
to
is to use the dakinis which are the
female and
wisdom energy forms and they know this
practice well the lineage holder is a
whole little
practice so you act as if you're a
dikini who knows how to do this practice
and it just
you get out of your own way and you you
can improve the efficiency of this
dissolving process
by imagining that yourself as a key
doing this process as you die
and then you can get achieve rainbow
light much quicker than say three days
you can do it in a single day
that's the second process the other two
processes are what are called
um the forest fire approach
and the awareness holders approach the
forest fire approach is a bypassing
approach to
trigel approach and what you do in that
is you
you imagine that you you when you're
dying you
light the body on fire and it's like the
body
residual substantiality of the body is
like fuel and it all burns up and
quickly burns up and disappears
and all that's left is bright light
rainbow lights in the sky
above where the body was that's called a
forest fire approach
and the fourth approach is
you don't have to purify the residual
substantiality of the body at all
because if you take the view that
the body was never anything other than
primarily pure right from the very
beginning this time
if you have that extreme experience you
don't have to do anything you can you
can intend
the body in in this original sacred form
without any substantiality just appears
rainbow light in the sky
so in the ningmah tradition in tibetan
buddhism for example there was a man
named garb dorji who was the
indian master who was the head of the
tradition and he had two students
one was manju shumitra and the other was
a man named sri simmo who was probably
the sambhav's teacher
so
so when he was
sickly and dying and he said i'm gonna
have to die now he told me
he might just shoot me to us with him he
said don't die you haven't given me all
the teachings yet
but he died and he transformed
immediately into golden light in his
form body and floated in the sky
and then he disappeared and my justice
usually said i didn't finish all the
teachings what are you going to what are
you going to show me i i don't have the
rest of the way
you have to give me this so he appeared
in the golden form
came back to him and he had a text made
of gold and light
he handed him the text and he said these
are the three essential points of the
rest of the teaching it's called the
ninjik and that was was passed on to
lineage it's been
unpacked in great detail but in england
and that's the what he did he he
came back and gave him the teachings
so that's called great consciousness
transference
and usually when a master can just at
will
turns into golden rainbow light that's
usually accompanied by
song and prayer and fragrant smells and
it's a whole
light show and sensory show and great
masters will do that kind of practice
so those are the four ways of
consciousness transference in this
tradition and the underlying implication
is
as miller rape says there's no dying to
be done
people who never really die they
live on and and they they they
become enlightened master becomes
awakened dharmakaya space which they
become part of that infinite field of
brilliantly knowing awakened awareness
love and they can
operate out of what's called gong bar
enlightened tension they can
they can intend any to come into any
plane of reality they want
in in multiple copies of themselves and
they can emanate and
guide others along the path and help
them out and then
and they have there's no dying process
they become what i call the young during
the immortal ones
that's true in buddhism and there's also
true endowedism
so that's the overview of the
practice in power and what i thought
we'd do now is we're going to switch
gears go back to the western model
so think about somebody who you've lost
in your life that you feel
unresolved about the loss
and you can settle into yourself and
close your eyes and focus on this
[Music]
and keep thinking about them in such a
way that you can make a connection with
[Music]
them
in fact you can think about them so
vividly did you actually feel like their
live presence in the room
think about them that vividly bring them
to mind so clearly
[Music]
and keep thinking about the special
connection you had with them
and now bring back the circumstances of
why this loss is unsettled for you still
what was it about the way that they died
or the nature of the relationship
that you feel most emotionally
unfinished about
and reflect now on what it is that you
feel most emotionally unfinished about
in this relationship
and imagine that person who's right in
front of you present
is if you open your eyes you could
actually sense their presence strongly
go ahead and do that
and you can give voice keep your thing
muted but
give voice out loud if you're by
yourself
to whatever it is that you feel you need
to most
express it feels most emotionally
unfinished about the relationship
or about the way they died
[Music]
go ahead and do that now bring to mind
what feels most emotionally unfinished
about the relationship
allow yourself to give voice to that is
if they could in their state of mind
currently
they could really understand what you're
saying
it may be about the way they died
it may be something about the loss it
may be something about the relationship
bring to mind and particularly what
feels most emotionally unfinished
and bring it to mind and say it in a
heartfelt way
and see what else comes to mind that
feels unfinished
and keep doing that until you start to
feel something shifting
[Music]
your voice to whatever feels the most
emotional unfinished
the feelings of that
it may be what you're angry about
it may be what you're sad about
there's something that feels unsettled
that you never get a chance to talk
about
[Music]
and imagine you have this one last
occasion to really give voice to this
in a way that will help this settle
giving voice to what feels most
emotionally unfinished in a heartfelt
way
and as there's some silence comes just
let's stay with that
stay with the connection you have with
them and then see
wait with yourself and see if anything
else comes up that feels unfinished
and if you find there's more give voice
to that too
now imagine that that person in the ways
that they know you so well
they have something they want you to
know
they've seen how you've suffered over
the years they've seen that
this hasn't really ended fully for you
they see that you haven't been able to
fully get over this
and they have some things to tell you
about that that will help you
so listen now to what they most want to
say to you
and let yourself really take it in
they see what needs to happen here
whatever the underlying thing that's
unsettled
whatever the conflict may be they're
addressing that directly
in terms of what you most need to hear
now see what else
needs to be said on either side
where there's more that you want to say
it feels still unsettled
whether there's something that they want
to say
continue that process until it's
something shifts
until you start to feel settled
now it's time to take leave
find a way of taking leave in the
relationship
you can keep the memories of what you
had it seems so precious
but other than that saying goodbye so
you can go your separate ways on your
journeys
find a way of taking leave now
and then imagine yourself now at some
time in the future
when you've gone on with your life
settle with this grief it's come to an
end and notice what's different about
your life
at that time in the future when you've
settled with this grieving process
imagine a scene in some detail
about the ways you're going about your
life and what's different about that
and then bring the process to a close
i'm going to account for one to five and
you can awaken yourself feeling settled
with your experience
five four
three two one fully awake and settle
with your experience
now this protocol has several steps in
it
the first step is to make a connection
with the
person that you've lost so you
think about the nature of the
relationship
and you think about it intimately with
the feelings
now many people will feel like that
they can feel that closeness so much
that the person is like present in the
room
early in the grieving process 70 of
people
will feel like the person is a
visitation to them
the person has just died so this is not
uncommon
you can imagine the connection so
vividly it's like they're in the room
we call that the revivification part of
it you're making it vivid
then the protocol begins with
the invitation to
bring to mind what feels most
emotionally unfinished
about the relationship
and the instructions are that specific
if you focus on what feels most
emotionally unfinished and give voice to
that
it becomes an occasion to finish it
to finish the processing of this so it
settles down
that's why we were in terms of what's
most emotionally unfinished
and you say they can give voice to it
now if i'm working on this one-on-one
with somebody
not like in a group of 60 people
i'll ask you to give voice to it out
loud so i can monitor the process
sometimes people will talk about
the circumstances of the dying process
sometimes they'll talk about
the loss of the relationship
but whatever it is that they're not
fully
have all the information they need in
order to process this
so giving voice to what's most
emotionally unfinished is a way of
starting to process that again
for example i i was doing a
psychology training workshop for three
days and i had a
senior psychologist take it
and then this first day she didn't come
back after the first day
and she called me two days later and
what she told me was that
she and her husband had some difficulty
with fertilization but
they eventually had a child
and they thought it was the only child
they had
and the child was 16 at the time and
while she came to this workshop with me
she got a call that night from the
police that when he was driving home he
crashed his car and burned and he died
so and she was suicidal after that
this was her only chance to have a kid
she put everything into this kid
so i told her to come in and we did this
grief protocol and she
first went over what
was missing from how he died
and she thought he might have reached
over as a country road it was a lot of
trees and he
wrapped his car on a tree and it burned
rapidly
she thought he might have been putting
in a cd and not paying attention to the
road
she was meaning making about the nature
of the dying
but one of the things she gave voice to
was she said you're drinking too much
and that was true so she understood an
explanation for this
which was quite plausible
but then she wanted to die
and she was suicidal
in the second part of the third part of
the protocol the first is the
revivification the second is giving
voice to what feels most emotional
unfinished and
she said you can't leave me i'm you know
you're the only thing i have in my life
outside of her husband
so she gave voice to that concern
in the next part you you let him give
voice to what he knows about her
that's a metaphor for unhooking the
conflict
it was freud and his contemporary carl
abraham who said that
complicated bereavement is necessarily
always about conflict in the
relationship you got to get at the
conflict
and the way you best way you get at the
conflict in this protocol is by
getting that person to give voice to
what the conflict is
rather than the person giving voice to
it it comes through the metaphor of the
other
they know the conflict they can see it
more better and what she's
what what he said to her was the
following
ma get a life you're in my face all the
time growing up especially when i was an
adolescent
and now you want to kill yourself and
follow me get in my face again
stay alive and give or get a life
now she knew that but the point was that
he had to say it that vividly
and once he could say that more vividly
that resolved the conflict sufficiently
that she could go on with her life
and the conflict got unhooked the next
part of the protocol is
leave taking you can keep the memories
you can't keep the relationship because
that's complicated believe me that's
delaying the believement
so it forces the issue of making the
difference between the memories
and the actual saying goodbye and leave
taking
and then the last part of the protocol
is you imagine some indefinite time in
the future when the person has finished
the grieving process
and they see what their life is like and
they can get on with their life again
beyond this grieving process it's a very
powerful protocol
it was originally developed in 1989 by
manthop in
australia we've used it a lot
it rarely ever does not work
so it's very powerful this is the best
of what i found in
grieving in the west
now you mentioned
cody the pandemic and that's something
it's
when we don't have funerals anymore
because of the social distancing
and a lot of times people in nursing
homes they just pile them in trucks now
it's not even a funeral there's no
burial service
so it's it's become a
cultural problem with almost 200 000
people
dying
so
as a culture
it's important to address this
and
one of the ways of doing it is
to imagine
the persons who've died all
releasing their indestructible essences
and wandering on their journey
and if you put the intention of your own
mind into guiding them along the path
it will soften their fear
a lot of people who die of covet they
can't breathe that's how they die
that's terrifying you comfort them
you do a visualization for all the
people who died of corvette and comfort
them
and that intention of your own mind
affects everybody else in the field
in tibetan buddhism unlike mindfulness
you open what i'll call simultaneous
mind you open up a level of mind that's
beyond
ordinary time and beyond
the limits of space
and in that little infinite timeless
boundless field
everything is contained within that
field
once you open up what we call
simultaneous mind it changes your ethics
because you can't think or do anything
that doesn't have an effect on everybody
else in the field
that's where the bodhisattva vowels come
in
that you recognize that you don't live
in a vacuum
and if you want to affect the everybody
in the field particularly those who have
died of covid then you intentionally
soothe them and send them on the journey
with less fear
it's a very powerful visualization
which i often do with my students during
this covert time
but i wanted to leave a time for
questions and answers i'm presenting you
a lot of stuff
both east and west in terms of how we
look at this but
i'd like to learn a little bit more
about what your own experience was with
the
glee protocol
well let's uh let's do that stowa style
and if you have any questions put them
in the chat
and uh we'll call on you and get you
unmuted and you can ask and if you don't
uh feel comfortable asking
um just write that and we can i can say
and thank you dan that was that was
awesome thank you
you want to speak more to that honest
yeah i haven't experienced
um anybody close to me that have that
have
died like family or friends but
really stuck with this addiction of
playing computer games a lot
and i actually use this as a way to
grieve letting
go of that and it felt to me
just as powerful and intimate and
visceral
as i don't know
what i would imagine it is it's an awful
application for it
yeah which is an observation obviously
it's creative it's creative thank you
for sharing that
what what what what did the computer
games give voice to when you when you
had the computer
games give voice to what they said they
weren't they want to see what they did
with the conflict it's a little bit
difficult to remember there
during the intense emotions but the gist
of it is
uh it's like you know when you go
through tough times
um and it's always been a comfort you
know comforter
always been been there for me
and
this idea of not
judging it as a bad thing but just
letting it be
what it was that comfort
and for it to be for me to it's like a
projection of myself like a mirror of
myself that i was facing and talking to
and it was like it was saying it was
actually preparing me for what comes
next
and um
i don't have to fear the lack of it
going forward with the challenges and
the suffering and the pain that might
be ahead and how to deal with it like
there are
other things it's honest
sorry i said that's honest yeah
emmanuel you had some feedback do i meet
yourself
hi thank you
i used the grieving protocol
say goodbye to my sister she's still
living but
um our our relationship needs to be let
go of
so i tapped into it really strong
and um i i love what manus just said
about like addictions because
there's something about my intimate
family
relationships that goes together with
the
food addiction i've been battling for
like 10 years
so i feel very raw
um very like tapped in all the way down
my chakras
um it feels good because i feel like i'm
being honest with myself right now
there's always what does she have to say
to you
she had to say um
it's okay i'm like crying face
she had to say that we're not equipped
to be a family for each other
but that doesn't mean i can't
have family it's just not her
and and that's that's acceptable to me
so it shifted yeah
as painful as it is it shifted and i i
know that
we've envisioned being
some kind of sister archetype to each
other and we've tried
so much and it's just not working
um but that's all right
you got to the heart of the matter it
feels different now doesn't it even
though it's painful
it's really painful but it's not
insurmountable
and uh i'm gonna play with this when my
freaking food addiction comes up again
like i'm just
just right on the verge of like
demi-goddess mastery
it's just a little awkward finishing
touches right now
but um i'm into it and i thank you for
everything you shared today
this is what we hope for it it unhooks
the conflict
and as painful as it may be it's shifted
anybody else a question from katie do
you want to meet yourself and
ask about comic memory choices sure hi
uh hi daniel thank you this was great
um i'm finding myself very intrigued by
the phrase karmic memory trace
and i'd love to learn more about that
like what
what are they um how they arise
and what non-engagement
with them means it means you set up the
view of this infinite expanse
of awakened awareness and everything
arises within that field
and as it arises you don't engage it
you just let it be there in awareness
when you engage it you form a karmic
memory choice
those comic memory traces become part of
what's called the storehouse mind
and they get activated
and they they once they get activated
they the tibetan word is minwa they
ripen
and they come out in the form of
influencing your state of mind and the
content of your mind in subtle ways
more obvious ways and eventually they
influence your behavior
so most of the content of your mind is
the ripening of comic memory traces
all the junk of the mind is the ripening
of comic memory traces
and you build it up over lifetimes
that's called a kunchi namsay the
storehouse consciousness in tibetan
so these practices allow you to set up
a view where you take the infinite vast
expanse in the right way
let everything arise within it without
engaging anything but with pure
awareness of it
and if you don't engage it as it comes
up it's like writing on water
it immediately disappears and then
another one comes up
and it becomes an automatic process
of release the average time it takes
about seven or eight years
to do that process if you combine it
with
inner fire practice when you're working
with the central channel system and
resolving the substantiality residual
substantiality of the body
you combine it with the what i call the
turgot bypassing visions
then you can clean this up in about two
years if you do all three of those
practices to set
you can finish everything in about three
years
so we have
now of our long-term students we have
about 30 students who
pretty far along with this process
and we're it's hard to run subjects now
we're waiting for the lab to open again
but we've identified the subjects and
we've
interviewed them and now when the lab
opens judd blue or
at brown university we'll run the
subjects and we'll look at the
what neural circuitry of
the complete purification and
flourishing of positive states
which i think has profound implications
for mental health
so that's what it's a very specific
practice it's a very
very advanced practice but in these
linear traditions the very specific
instructions that are given and i've
done this for 50 years
so
i've learned them along the way
that answer your question
yeah yeah sort of i i feel like there's
a
there's an interesting point where i'm
getting stuck on like engaging with
karmic memory traces versus like
engaging with the world
and it seems like it would be possible
to be completely unengaged with the
world and in like a dark cave somewhere
but still engaging with all of your
you know psychological but we don't do
that in these traditions
yeah the true expression of the
authenticity of realization is conduct
and so that's where i'm sort of i'm
wondering about like engaging with the
world
from a place of non-engagement with
karmic memory traces
exactly yeah then you can truly serve
people
because you don't get in your own way
but the true measure of
if if people get a taste of awakening
how do we know it's authentic
it may be just purely conceptual we say
if it moves your heart
is accompanied by gratitude
and appreciation then it's likely to be
authentic
but the only true test of it is conduct
people who are
realize they leave a wake of positive
influence around them
it affects their life everything in
their life and everybody around him
that's what we look for in terms of the
genuineness of this practice
so it's not like you go off in a cave
and do that
by yourself it's not that's not how it's
done
thank you
um isaias uh you have a good question
yeah thank you i thank you daniel and
cody for this
event um just a bit of of context
my question uh my family went through a
lot of
tragedy in 2019 um
due to the various deaths and i for
geographical reasons i haven't been able
to see them
since that and so i'm wondering if any
specific
trainings necessary to guide people
through the grieving protocol
or if it should be guided specifically
by a
trained professional it should be done
by a clinician
okay where is where's your family in
mexico
well
they speak english no
that's why when we were going through
this i was like trying to translate all
your things into
spanish directly but i mean
yeah i gotta see if i can find somebody
for you
that speaks spanish and knows the grief
protocol
uh if you don't mind daniel i'll connect
um you and isaias
um and see if we can uh have a follow-up
connection for that yeah
thank you um key
has a question she says thank you so
much for inviting daniel
um oh you spoke of daniel you spoke of
three internal poes
uh can you clarify the third one the
rebirth one of content
well the first one there's no content
it's just pure field of awareness which
we already
follow unconscious in but if you
recognize that
as a lucid bright field of awakened
awareness then that game over
the second one is the sound and light
show and you have to see the
the lights as insubstantial not not
as as real and out there and the third
one
mental content comes back but it starts
with the experience of what we call a
mental body
that you have your senses back you can
now see people who still part of the
world
you've left the world but you can see
them you can hear them
but they don't respond to you and
and if you think about going someplace
you're immediately there bush you're
immediately there
so you figure out from that that this
mental body has lost the physical body
and that you infer from that that you've
died
and then you'll get a series of
visions about what world you're going to
end up in
and if you can see those visions as
empty constructions of mind
then you can get off the wheel but the
tendency is you get caught up in all
that stuff
and you end up getting reborn again
start starting the whole thing over
again like groundhog day
so that's what i was saying
cue how was that
um
it made sense but
groundhog day you know i haven't seen
that movie
it's one of the classics yeah i figured
um so how
how does one
get out of groundhog day i guess is the
question
in tibetan buddhism you see everything
is empty which means that it's
you see everything as a mental
construction of mind
we tend to make the world solid
we tend to make it as if it's out there
and that's a view that's reinforced by
sciences if there's a world out there we
measure constancies in that world
but buddhism what if that world is just
all mental constructions
what if we're seeing is our own mental
constructions
and that's the view that's taken
so if you if you see them as mental
constructions you can go beyond the
mental constructions
so they don't interfere
but we get caught up in the mental
constructions of our mind we dwell in
them we get caught up in them
there's a heart sutra
it goes like this in sanskrit gate
gate paradigati para samgate bodhis faha
there's your entire path literally means
gone gone gone way beyond gone way way
beyond ooh what a realization
that's the exact translation from the
sanskrit this is what it means
in our everyday life we get so caught up
in thought we spend most of our day
caught up in thought
we tend to take thought as real we
forget it's mental construction
but if i look at it a certain way i see
the thought as
just a mental construction and i start
operating out of not the
thought i don't get caught up in it so
much it's not operating out of the field
of awareness
cleanup of thought
it's the first gote awareness gone
beyond thought
but i get caught up in my sense of self
i get caught up in damnedness
a lot of the day i operate out of self
mode
whenever i do emptiness of self i see
beyond that itself and i operate under
field awareness it's not a cleanup of
thought but has cleaned up a sense of
self
this is second gote awareness itself
is my basis of operation gone beyond
personal identity but now i get caught
up in time
i tend to take the time is real and
space is real
but if i look at it the field is
a field of timeless limitless boundless
awareness
i go beyond that construction of time
now i'm operating out of that timeless
field of awareness which is huge
and limitless and changeless
but i still tend to localize
consciousness within that
and when i set up the view a certain way
i can shift
out of that localization and become that
unbounded wholeness
that's the point that i open up to
awakening
that's a big shift so
what the mantra means is i get caught up
in thought i go beyond thought
i get caught up in self i go beyond self
i get caught up in time and space i go
beyond time and space i get caught up in
localization of consciousness i go
beyond that
and now i'm operating out of this
limitless huge
boundless field of timeless lucidly
bright awakened awareness love
that's my true nature i found my way
home
so we say that emptiness is the path
because
as long as i see everything is
substantial and out there
i don't even look at it this way but
once i open up to viewing it from this
perspective
i can go beyond all those seemingly
substantial structures of the mind
and all the reactivity involved in that
and i'm genuinely free
of all that so it's to find the way out
or if you like the way home
that's what these paths are about thank
you
not so much yeah
q um maybe time for one or two more um
jacob you have a question you want to
meet yourself
how do you know nobody dies
you have to go through the dying process
and stay
awake during it then you know
so it's experience is your source
of what so your experience is your
source
yes
thank you then you can come back in any
form you want
i just call [ __ ] on you all over the
place
because you're talking about no
it makes me angry because this is very
misleading and very powerful stuff
that you're saying it's powerfully
misleading
you're talking about releasing yourself
from mental constructs but everything
you just talked about
was constructive
so all i can do is struggle without
glaringly hypocritical
thank you
can't please everybody
um thank you tanya you have a question
so daniel thank you for your
presentation um you had presented to us
two starkly different
contrasting ways to see
dying yeah wondering if
the populations in the east
view dying differently as a result
than those of us in the west like and
there's a there's a fundamental
difference
in in in seeing dying in in the
populations
i don't know about that all i know is
the people who practice or how they see
it but whether people who don't practice
see it that way i don't know that
um next up max um
you had some feelings do you want to
talk about uh talk about your feels
ah can't use your mic um and it's night
there well thank you
um i'm glad you're i'm glad you're
feeling things
um see you next up uh let's see time
okay ryan
hi thanks so much daniel for coming and
talking to us this was a great
presentation i really appreciated it
thanks cody for facilitating uh i work
as a hospice nurse in
an inpatient setting so
i'm around deaf and dying quite a bit
and wondering
how to maybe incorporate
maybe not necessarily the clinical
practice but
some of the concepts and ideas
that you're using to facilitate death
and dying in
a better way or a more holistic way
here in the west thanks
well the best preparation for dying is
the experience of awakening
in practice because then you use the
dying process to awaken
that's the best practice short of that
then as people who are
still alive and not going through the
dying process
we can still keep people in a better
state of mind when they go into the
dying process
as they dismantle thought and they
dismantle perception
then there are a couple things you want
to do about that
there's a point where in in the western
literature i'm dying
where people sort of get it that they're
dying
and they want to turn inward that's the
point that we often don't recognize in
the hospice process you know
probably what i'm talking about and at
that point
families and doctors interfere
the person wants to just prepare to die
now they know that that's
giving up hope of living
and we should facilitate helping them
die at that point
and recognize those signs and let the
family members let them go
but oftentimes we either family members
will for their own needs will continue
to
push the issue or doctors will try and
involve
them in life-saving things that will
interfere with the process
at that point we should let them go and
we should prepare them to die
now how to prepare them to die is to
comfort them
to remove the fear and uncertainty
if you can go through what they're
likely to experience as they
are in the dying process that's useful
my first route llama in the 1970s
he did something unusual when he died he
let us be with him
and he gave us a running commentary on
what he was doing
up to the point he couldn't talk anymore
and then
before you got to the point of not
talking anymore he told us what was
going to come next he gave us all the
previews
so that's the teacher's greatest
teaching is
to teach others how to die
so you can do a lot in your hospice work
so whole world it opens up there
can i ask a follow-up sure is that all
right
um i'm just curious if
how you see the evolution of death and
dying
um as as culture changes
and um
yeah just the evolution of death and
dying in the west
maybe in relation to some of the
teachings
well
ahmed baba was the great master
in buddhism and he wrote texts for the
future
what are called secret treasure texts
one of them was discovered in the 14th
century was by kavalingpa
he left it behind about half of them
been discovered
and that one contained all the teachings
on what you know is the tibetan book of
the dead
and what he foresaw is that at times in
history people get weirded out about
dying and they couldn't talk about it
so they needed teachings on it
so that those teachings were made
available
we know what the experience of the
stages of dying are they
described in great detail
there's a manual for how you go through
the dying process it's described in
terms of how
each element dissolves into the next
element
but what the experiences are that go
along with that
that's the internal consciousness
transference practice that i
i i went over
that's available in a book called that
we translated called
the self-arising threefold embodiment of
enlightenment
it's a collection of all the advanced
cave and hermitage yogi texts
in one one one collection
so there's a whole detailed description
of
how you use the dyeing process
i think we may have time for just one
more um
vicente to pronounce it right
yep hi dan thanks thanks for your time
uh man
cody and team for organizing um just a
quick question about
possibly a more detailed uh explanation
of the consciousness
transference process so for example
during the dying process of the 13th
dalai lama like for example how would
that
go from point a 13 dalai lama to point b
like the current dalai lama like which
boa is their intention behind it and so
forth
well the trouble with that is it gets
politicized but
um what what will happen is if
he decides to come back
he will leave his body enter
awaken dharmakaya space and then
put the intention into coming back in a
certain form
but a great master can come back in any
form that they want they come back in
multiple forms
it's it's on what we call gongbong light
and intention
so they can make the determination of
where they want to come back
rahab tulku who was my roommate
he was the emanation of parmesa
and he came in the 14th century
reincarnated every every lifetime
at the same geographic area so he could
continue to teach them
but he said that he's not going to
continue that there he's going to come
back in the west now
so how he shows up what form he'll show
up i don't know anything about that yet
because he died
earlier this year so it's too early yet
but he's going to continue in the west
so the process of
how one selects a great master
that's difficult because it's often
politically politicized
i'll tell you a story about that i
i met a llama once who
told me a story of when the
chinese were going to invade tibet
the pancha lama who was an adviser to
the dalai lama
dalai lama was a teenager at the time
they said we need to go
to beijing and talk directly with mao
and negotiate a peaceful settlement
there's no
reason to have our country destroyed so
they went on a trip
and the llama that i know
three days on the trip had a prophetic
dream that they would be ambushed he
told the dalai lama this is a trap
you have to leave so he disguised him
and took him back on a donkey
and the punch and llama went on with the
journey
and there was an ambush and he was
placed in the house of rest in beijing
for the rest of his life
he then died and came back as a young
kid
in china and both the dalai lama's
tradition and the chinese agreed that
this was the
real punching lama
and he was educated by the chinese
when he was eight years old not
still remembering his former lifetimes
he escaped
china by himself as an eight-year-old
boy got out of the country and showed up
at the dalai lama's palace
and sent him back that's never been
disclosed
by the chinese because they
put in a fake one and they're going to
say that they they don't have the real
punching llama but the punch in llamas
back no one knows where he is so it
doesn't get killed
but it takes the politicization out of
this process
so there'll be a new dalai lama at some
point
but he's publicly saying he's not going
to come back he just want to get into
this cat fight with the chinese about it
dan there is um anyway i have only a
couple more minutes um
but there is this one uh there's kind of
a call for
call for a question to um to address
some of the epistemological concerns
revolt revolving uh jacob who
you know had his uh had his own
skepticality
about um these teachings in general and
if there's any
anything you'd like to say to it or you
can say to it to
appease um these minds
well all i can do is tell you what my
experience is
over 50 years of doing this practice
if he thinks it's all fake news and and
he's angry about that there's nothing i
can do about that state of mind
all i can do is talk what i know
um i think that's gonna
put us right at about time um daniel i
want to thank you um
thank you so much for for doing this
this was uh this is really fantastic and
i think a lot of people got a
lot of beautiful uh beautiful
experiences out of it
um you want to say any last uh any last
words or
anything else i'm gonna i'm gonna post
your um website pointingoutway.org into
the chat if people would like to learn
some more about daniel
anything last you'd like to say before i
hand it to peter to close us off
no just be sensitive to all the people
who are dying in this
pandemic i think
we don't have leadership that's
sensitive to that at the moment
we need to be careful about all the
people who are dying
and not let them live die
insignificantly
thank you again forgotten okay
good thank you everybody
uh peter would you like to close us out
yeah uh thank you uh cody francine today
thank you daniel
a lot of rawness was expressed today
and uh if you want to process it
together as a group you can head over to
our
uh discord channel uh there's a few if
you're familiar with discord there's
like a video option so
you just have to go there go to the
rules channel give it a thumbs up and
all the other channels will open up for
you you can continue this conversation
and maybe what a rose process a lot of
things
uh there to talk about some upcoming
events
tomorrow at 7 30 pm eastern time daniel
schmuckenberger
defense making mensch is coming in um
to do a session on dharma inquiry he has
a series of questions excellent
questions
to kind of flesh out our what what one's
dharma is in life
so that's tomorrow 7 p.m eastern time
and then on tuesday sarah ness
[Music]
who is sort of like the epicenter of all
this authentic relating
kind of movement scene she has something
called quarantine and community and
exploration
and that's september 1st tuesday 6 30 pm
eastern time uh we have many many events
on the website
uh you can check it out and um you know
if you'd like to support the stoa if you
like this session and you'd like more
sessions like this you go to our patreon
page
which is in the chat so again um
and in the manual the store is lit it is
lit
all right everyone thank you so much for
coming out today
thanks everyone bye everyone
[Music]
you